{"tossups": [{"question": "One leader of this kingdom was called the \u201cmute king,\u201d and a curse believed to be cast on the ruling dynasty of this kingdom supposedly explains why alternating generations of its Wadiyar Dynasty never had children. The first iron-cased rockets were used by this kingdom, leading the British to reverse-engineer the Congreve Rocket. This kingdom\u2019s ruler Hyder Ali fought the Maratha Confederacy and the British East India Company. Tipu Sultan ruled, for ten points, what kingdom in southern India?", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Mysore</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man declared that \u201cthe road to holiness necessarily passes through the world of action\u201d in his memoirs, titled Markings. The Soviet Union attempted to unseat this man with a three-person \u201ctroika\u201dwith veto power. Union Miniere may have killed this man, whose DC-6 was shot down as he flew for peace talks with Moise Tshombe\u2019s Katangese troops. He was posthumously awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for his work in the Congo Crisis. For ten points, identify this Swedish politician, the second UN Secretary-General.", "answer": "Dag<b> Hammarskjold</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The ship<em> Primrose</em> was attacked in this island chain, which was once colonized by Austria as Theresia. Sher Ali Afridi stabbed the 6th Lord Mayo to death in these islands, where a prison known as the \u201cblack waters\u201d was used to house British political prisoners. The Cellular Jail was in this island chain, where missionary John Allen Chau was killed by the Sentinelese in 2018. Port Blair is the capital of, for ten points, what island chain west of Myanmar whose indigenous people are some of the last uncontacted people in the world?", "answer": "<b> Andaman</b> Islands (accept<b> Andaman and Nicobar</b> islands; do not accept or prompt on North Sentinel Island)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man gained the support of<em> Century</em> magazine editor Robert Johnson after the two of them took a trip to Tuolumne [too-AWL-um-nee] Meadows. This man worked with Henry Senger to form a resistance group to the Hetch Hetchy Dam. A famous photograph of this man shows him standing atop Glacier Point with Theodore Roosevelt. In 1906, this man successfully campaigned for Yosemite to be put under federal control. For ten points, name this Scottish-American naturalist who founded the Sierra Club.", "answer": "John<b> Muir</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler debated Otanes and Megazubus over different governmental systems until he was chosen to be king because his slave Oebares made his horse neigh first at sunrise. This ruler overthrew Bardiya, who was possibly impersonated by Gaumata. Nebuchadnezzar III fought a ruler of this name, who created the first satrapies from a tax system inherited by Cyrus the Great. The Behistun Inscription was created by, for ten points, what ruler who led the first Persian invasion of Greece?", "answer": "<b> Darius the Great</b> (accept<b> Darius I</b>; prompt on Darius)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Wulfing Cache artifacts may have originated at a site in this city that housed several workshops specializing in copper pieces. A circular wooden \u201chenge\u201d once sat on what is now a burial site south of this city; that site contained the grave of a man who was buried atop beads arranged to resemble a falcon. Birdman artifacts typical of this city\u2019s Mississippian culture have been found in excavations of this city\u2019s Mound 72. For ten points, name this pre-Columbian city in modern Illinois, east of St Louis.", "answer": "<b> Cahokia</b> (accept<b> Cahokia</b> Mounds)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In one of this campaign\u2019s initiatives, the city of Akmolinsk was renamed Tselinograd. This campaign mandated the construction of new<em> sovkhozes</em> in the Caucasus and Siberia. Dry conditions in Kazakhstan prevented the successful development of monoculture during this campaign, which sought to catch the United States in grain production by 1960. For ten points, name this campaign in which Nikita Khrushchev attempted to bolster the agricultural output of the Soviet Union by plowing previously unused farmland.", "answer": "<b> Virgin Lands</b> Campaign (accept<b> Osvoyeniye tseliny</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Some critics believed Khrushchev developed the Virgin Lands Campaign as a way to steal credit from this politician, who served as premier without party leadership for two years until he was removed in a power struggle in 1955. This man\u2019s 1957 coup against Khrushchev failed.", "answer": "Georgy<b> Malenkov</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<em>Gone With the Wind</em> was re-released in 1961 in part to re-take the US box office record from this film. <em>Around the World in 80 Days</em> and<em> The King and I</em> beat this film in all of its nominated Oscar categories except Best Special Effects, which it won in part for a scene created by playing footage of spilling water backwards. ABC has annually broadcast this film on Easter weekend since 1973. Cecil B. DeMille\u2019s last film was, for ten points, what epic about the life of Moses?", "answer": "The<b> Ten Commandments</b> BONUS:<em> The Ten Commandments</em> stars this man as Moses. He also starred in<em> Ben-Hur</em>, and he led the National Rifle Association for five years before his death in 2008. ANSWER: Charlton<b> Heston</b> (accept John Charles<b> Carter</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Mohamed Hamdan Dagalo has led one of the groups in this conflict, a militia of Abbala and Baggara people known as \u201cevil men on horseback.\u201d The Justice and Equality Movement and the SLA are rebel groups opposed by government forces in this conflict. UN peacekeepers have been based in el-Fashir and Nyala during this conflict, in which hundreds of thousands of people have been killed. Omar al-Bashir carried out, for ten points, what crime against humanity in western Sudan?", "answer": "<b> Darfur</b> genocide (or<b> Darfur</b> War; do not accept answers about South Sudan)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>An author from this country was imprisoned for writing the article \u201cThoughts on March 8,\u201d which criticized this country\u2019s leaders for leaving their wives. Another author from this</b> <b>country wrote the novels</b><em><b> To Live</b></em><b> and (+)</b> <em><b>Brothers</b></em><b>, which depict struggle sessions in this</b> <b>country. Another author from this country wrote the novel (*)</b><em> Red Sorghum</em>, which ends with a war between this country and Japan. For ten points, name this home country of Ding Ling, Yu Hua, and Mo Yan, who depicted this country\u2019s revolution under Mao Zedong.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> (or<b> Zhongguo</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>After this event, one victim issued a statement claiming that the American people had to decide \u201cWhether ours shall continue to be a government of laws and not of men.\u201d Leon Jaworski took over the central figure\u2019s position after this event, which occurred after a refusal of the (+) Stennis Compromise. Expansion of an investigation into the activities of the Plumbers was one of the causes of this event, which was ultimately carried out by (*) </b>acting Attorney General Robert Bork. For ten points, name this event in which Archibald Cox was fired while acting as special prosecutor of the Watergate investigation.", "answer": "<b> Saturday Night Massacre</b> (prompt on descriptive answers of Nixon\u2019s firing of Archibald Cox and/or the resignations of Elliot Richardson and/or William Ruckelshaus)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man supposedly fell into a \u201cviolent passion\u201d and massacred the people of Limoges [lim-ohzh]. This man was denied reinforcements against the Duke of Alencon after the king</b> <b>declared \u201clet the (+)</b> <b>boy win his spurs.\u201d John II demanded this man\u2019s surrender after</b> <b>boy win his spurs.\u201d John II demanded this man\u2019s surrender after</b> <b>outflanking him, but this man declined and instead routed John\u2019s forces at (*)</b> <b>outflanking him, but this man declined and instead routed John\u2019s forces at (*)</b> Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay]. This heir to Edward III died of dysentery in 1376, allowing Richard II to take the throne instead. For ten points, name this English general of the Hundred Years\u2019 War who became known for his dark armor.", "answer": "<b> Edward the Black Prince</b> (accept<b> Edward of Woodstock</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist created an oil painting in which a bicyclist frightens horses drawing a carriage as they maneuver out of the way. This artist of</b><em><b> The Right of the Road</b></em><b> depicted the opening of the Wounded Knee massacre in an illustration for (+)</b><em><b> Harper\u2019s Weekly</b></em><b>. This artist, who sometimes collaborated with his friend, author Owen Wister, created a bronze sculpture depicting a man (*) </b> struggling to keep hold of the mane of a horse. For ten points, name this artist known for his scenes of the Old American West, such as<em> The Bronco Buster</em>.", "answer": "Frederic<b> Remington</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Prior to this event, its perpetrator admitted that he was \u201cgoing to strike a strong blow. Things are going to get hot,\u201d and, in a meeting with Jean Drepeau, noted, \u201cI have to speak to those people who are calling for me.\u201d In the wake of this event, (+) Pierre Trudeau was labeled \u201cthe enemy of the \u2018French fact\u2019\u201d. This incident, which took place during Expo 67, took place on a balcony at (*)</b> Montreal City Hall. Lester Pearson issued the retort \u201cThe people of Canada<em> are</em> free\u201d after, for ten points, what July 1967 international incident in which Charles de Gaulle stoked Qu\u00b4eb\u00b4ecois nationalism with a controversial four-word phrase?", "answer": "Charles de Gaulle proclaiming<b> Vive le Qu\u00b4ebec libre!</b> (or<b> Long live free Qu\u00b4ebec!</b>; prompt on descriptions of de Gaulle visiting Montreal, Canada) (6) <b>This composer included characters like Human Frailty in his Homer-inspired opera</b> <em><b>The Return of Ulysses to his Homeland</b></em><b>. This composer used an excerpt from</b><em><b> Jerusalem</b></em> <em><b>Delivered</b></em><b> for an opera that contains one of the (+)</b> <b>earliest uses of tremolo. Ottavia sings</b> <b>\u201cAddio, Roma\u201d in an opera by this composer about the crowning of Nero\u2019s mistress,</b><em><b> The </b><b>Coronation of Poppea</b></em><b>. (*)</b> Eurydice fails to return to the mortal world in the most famous work by, for ten points, what Italian composer of<em> L\u2019Orfeo</em>, one of the earliest surviving operas? ANSWER: Claudio (Giovanni Antonio)<b> Monteverdi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this battle, Charles Wellford revealed a road to cartographer Jedidiah Hotchkiss to shield forces from enemy pickets. John Reynolds made a daylight march to the Rappahannock</b> <b>in this battle while Jubal Early desperately tried to keep John (+)</b> <b>Sedgwick at bay. Prior</b> <b>Sedgwick at bay. Prior</b> <b>to this battle, a general commented, \u201cMy plans are perfect. May God have (*)</b> <b>to this battle, a general commented, \u201cMy plans are perfect. May God have (*)</b> mercy on General Lee, for I will have none.\u201d Joseph Hooker lost despite a Union numerical advantage at, for ten points, what May 1863 battle near Fredericksburg where friendly fire caused the death of \u201cStonewall\u201dJackson?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Chancellorsville</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was aided by the weapons specialists Mustafa Rumi and Ustad Ali, who were sent by Selim I to coax this man away from an alliance with the Safavids. This man ended a ten year drinking binge shortly before the Battle of (+) Khanwa, where he defeated the Rana Sanga who challenged his power. After contesting Muhammed Shaybani for (*) </b> Ferghana and Samarkand, this man was invited to launch an invasion by Daulat Khan. Ibrahim Lodi lost the first Battle of Panipat to, for ten points, what founder of the Mughal Empire?", "answer": "Zahir ud-Din Muhammad<b> Babur</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}